Guide to the Videos by Latina Women: New Visions of the Globalizing South Collection, 2003 RL.11099
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Videos by Latina Women: New Visions of the Globalizing South
2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kalow, Nancy
RL.11099
40 items Electronic files including 11 PDFs, 17 TIFFs, and 12 MOVs
8.27 Gigabytes
Videos and fieldnotes created by students in 2003, in the CDS Continuing Education course "Visual Storytelling" in collaboration with 8 Latina immigrants. The course was taught by CDS Faculty member Nancy Kalow.
Arrangement
Alphabetical
Historical note
In April of 2003, UNC selected Nancy Kalow as a 2003-2004 Fellow in their Rockefeller Residency Fellowship Program, "Reimagining Civil Society in an Era of Globalization: the American South in Applied Humanities Perspectives." Kalow's project, done in partnership with the Center for Documentary Studies, was titled "Videos by Latina Women: New Visions of the Globalizing South." The resulting set of documentary videos explored Latina culture, traditions, community concerns, folklife, music, family, and more. The project goals, as Clemencia Rodriguez said in her essay on Latin American women producing video stories, included "personal and group empowerment, demystification of mainstream media, reversal of power roles, and increasing collective strength." A measure of the project's impact is in the fact that the Latina women continued to produce video work after the class ended. For example, they wrote and produced a video Public Service Announcement about the hazards of drunk driving; this PSA was played extensively on Univision.
The project taught video production to eight recently-arrived Latina immigrant women with the mentoring of six local videographers, all women. The Latina women were Ana Maria Silva, Antonia Monroy, Maria de Lourdes Ruiz Loera, Rocio Callejas Angeles, Marisol Marquez, Hilda Badillo, Alicia Garcia Solis, and Tana Hoffman. The mentors were Nancy Kalow, Duke student Jennifer Hasvold, UNC student Rebecca O'Doherty, and three CDS Continuing Studies students, Phoebe Brush, Erika Simon, and Lisa Croucher. The group of 14 women met weekly during the fall of 2003 on Saturday mornings; Kalow taught her "Visual Storytelling" documentary videography class entirely in Spanish with the assistance of Phoebe Brush and Erika Simon. The Latina participants had complete control of content, production, and editing.
The Rockefeller Fellowship provided free instruction for the course as well as funding eight camcorders and tripods, transportation and babysitting, access to editing, and other technical requirements. Classroom space was provided by CDS, and the final public presentations were made at Duke and UNC. A series of additional public presentations allowed for meaningful cultural exchange, with sharing of the documentary videos accompanied by discussion with audiences.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Videos by Latina Women collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
Materials include digital video, photographic, and text files for the project "Videos by Latina Women: New Visions of the Globalizing South," created as part of Nancy Kalow's Rockefeller Residency Fellowship. The 12 MOV video files are the documentaries produced during the year by the projects collaborators, including eight recently-arrived Latina immigrant women and the videographers who served as their mentors. The 17 TIFF photograph files are portraits of the creators and shots of them working. The 11 PDF text files include fieldnotes kept by the mentors, interview transcripts, correspondence, release forms, and papers, presentations, and conclusions about the project.
Hispanic Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; Audiovisual materials; Digital moving image formats; Video recordings; Documentary films; Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Kalow, Nancy
- Videos, 2003
  Arrangement
  Arrangement is alphabetical.
  Scope and Contents
  Twelve MOV video files documenting the lives of the eight Latina women participating in the project.
  - Rocio Callejas Angeles
    - Pola, 2003; 00:04:16 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file Pola.mov)
    - Mi Papa Esta Cantando, 2003; 00:04:17 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file RocioPapaSubtitled.mov)
  - Hilda Badillo
    - Beto, 2003; 00:02:06 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file BetoJan08.mov)
    - Imagine, 2003; 00:03:07 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file Imagine.mov)
  - Tana Hoffman
    - El Centro, 2003; 00:03:13 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file ElCentro.mov)
  - Maria de Lourdes Ruiz Loera
    - La Quinta, 2003; 00:02:31 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file LourdesLaQuinta.mov)
  - Marisol Marquez
    - La Fiesta de Tere, 2003; 00:02:08 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file MarisolParty.mov)
  - Antonia Monroy
    - Diligencia, 2003; 00:03:13 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file ShortDiligencia.mov)
    - Tinting, 2003; 00:01:49 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file tinting.mov)
  - Ana Maria Silva
    - Comida Mexicana, 2003; 00:05:36 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file subtitledAnaComidas.mov)
    - La se単ora Ana Maria le hace una entrevista jarocha al se単or Julio, 2003; 00:02:06 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file JulioInterview.mov)
  - Alicia Garcia Solis
    - Alfredo, 2003; 00:04:35 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0001, Video-file shortAlfredo.mov)
- Photographs
  Seventeen TIFF photograph files including portraits of the filmmakers and shots taken during production.
  - Portraits
    - Rocio Callejas Angeles, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Hilda Badillo, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Tana Hoffman, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Maria de Lourdes Ruiz Loera, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Marisol Marquez, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Antonia Monroy, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Ana Maria Silva, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
    - Alicia Garcia Solis, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0002)
  - Process
    - AnaProcess_h, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - Hilda_b, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - LourdesAliciaProcess_i, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - MarisolProcess_f, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - PhoebeProcess_e, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - Process_d, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - RocioAliciaProcess_g, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - RocioTable_a, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
    - TanaErika_c, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0003)
- Administrative materials
  Eleven PDF text files including field notes, correspondence, and other administrative materials related to the project.
  - Becky O'Doherty fieldnotes and correspondence, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Erika Simon project field notes and correspondence, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Erika Simon spring and summer field notes and correspondence, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Jennifer Hasvold fieldnotes and correspondence, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Lisa Croucher fieldnotes and correspondence, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Nancy Kalow fieldnotes, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Phoebe Brush fieldnotes, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - English interview transcripts, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Latina video project materials and correspondence, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - Latina video project release forms, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)
  - UNC Rockefeller Grant for Latina video project, 2003 (Digital-materials RL11099-SET-0004)